斯尼德公司向您奉上最诚挚的哀悼 先生
Sneed and Company offer their sincerest condolences, sir,
愿您坚强面对这般痛苦的时刻
in this most trying hour.
祖母她晚年还是很幸福的 斯尼德先生
Grandmama had a good innings, Mr Sneed.
她曾如此充满活力
She was so full of life,
我简直不敢相信她去了
I can't believe she's gone.
不是去了 雷德帕斯先生
Not gone, Mr Redpath, sir.
睡着了而已
Merely sleeping.
我能一个人静一静吗
May I have a moment?
当然可以
Yes, of course.
我就在隔壁 您如有需要可以叫我
I shall be in the next, er, room should you require anything.
又来了
Oh, no!
住手
No!
格温妮丝
Gwyneth!
快下来 又复活了一个
Get down here now! We've got another one!
神秘博士第一季第三集
借尸还魂
按住那个 -我正按着呢
Hold that one down! - I'm holding this one down!
那就两个都按着
Well, hold them both down!
我够不着
It's not gonna work.
我承诺了给你时间旅行你就这么回报我
Oi! I promised you a time machine and that's what you get.
你见识过了未来
Now you've seen the future,
让我们回过过去吧 1860年听起来如何
let's have a look at the past... 1860, How does 1860 sound?
1860年怎么了
What happened in 1860?
我不知道 一起去看看 抓住 要去了
I don't know, let's find out! Hold on... here we go!
格温妮丝
Gwyneth!
你死哪去了 丫头
Where are you, girl?
格温妮丝
Gwyneth!
你哪去了 我喊了你半天了
Where've you been? I was shouting.
我一直在马厩 先生 在为我们的马碎冰
Been in the stable, sir, breaking the ice from Samson.
那你再回去 给它穿戴上马具
Well, get back in there and harness him up!
要去干什么 先生
Whatever for, sir?
又有尸体活过来了
The stiffs are getting lively again.
雷德帕斯先生的祖母 又起来活蹦乱跳了
Mr Redpath's grandmother, she's is up there on her feet,
现在不知所踪 我们得赶紧找到她
and out there somewhere, on the streets, we've got to find her.
丢脸啊斯尼德先生 还要闹几次
Mr Sneed, for shame, how many more times?
简直天理难容啊
It's ungodly!
看我做什么 又不是我的错 赶紧
Don't look at me like it's MY fault. Now come on,
快点去 她都86岁了 走不了太远的
hurry up, she was 86, she can't have got far!
那雷德帕斯先生怎么办
What about Mr Redpath?
你想好怎么处理他了吗
Did you deal with him?
没有
No.
她已经把他"处理"了
SHE did.
太糟了 先生
That's awful, sir.
我知道我没资格说这话
I know it's not my place,
所以请原谅我这般不懂规矩 先生
and please forgive me for talking out of turn, sir,
但这事已经快不受控制了
but this is getting beyond now.
这房子肯定遭了什么厄运
Something terrible is happening in this house
我们必须得求助
and we've got to get help.
当然得求助
And we will,
但要先把那老太太抓回来锁住 别出事了
as soon as I've got that dead old woman locked up and safe and sound.
别再多嘴了 丫头
Now, stop prevaricating, girl.
备好灵车 我们这就收尸去
Get the hearse ready. We're going bodysnatching.
天呐 -你还好吗
Blimey! - Telling me! You all right?
我觉得还好 没摔坏
Yeah, I think so. Nothing broken.
我们到了吗 到哪了
Did we make it? Where are we?
我成功了 真该给我颁块奖牌
I did it! Give the man a medal.
地球那不勒斯 1860年12月24日
Earth, Naples, December 24th, 1860.
太诡异了 这是圣诞节啊
That's so weird. It's Christmas.
请吧
All yours.
但就好像
But it's like...
好好想想吧
think about it, though.
1860年的圣诞节仅有一次 就这一次
Christmas 1860 happens once, just once, and then it's...
然后就永不再现 再也没有第二次了
gone, it's finished, it'll never happen again.
但对你例外
Except for you.
你可以回到过去 重度那些已经逝去的时光
You can go back and see days that are dead and gone.
回到千万个日落之前
A hundred thousand sunsets ago.
难怪你安定不下来
No wonder you never stay still.
这样活着挺好的
Not a bad life.
有人陪着更好
Better with two.
那就去吧 -慢着慢着
Come on then! - Oi, oi, oi!
你干什么去 -去1860年啊
Where d'you think you're going? - 1860.
你穿成这样出去会引发暴乱的 芭芭丽娜
Go out there dressed like that, you'll start a riot, Barbarella.
那边有个衣柜
There's a wardrobe through there,
进左边第一个门 再右边第二个门
1st left, 2nd right,
然后左边第三个门
third on the left,
然后直走下楼梯
go straight ahead, under the stairs,
经过一堆箱子 左边第五个门 快去
past the bins, fifth door on your left. Hurry up!
连个影子都没有
Not a sign.
她哪去了
Where is she?
人间蒸发了呗 先生 还能哪去了
She's vanished into the ether, sir. Where can she be?
你来告诉我她去哪了 -您什么意思
You tell me, girl. - What do you mean?
格温妮丝 你知道我什么意思
Gwyneth, you know full well.
我不能 先生 -快用你的天眼
No, sir, I can't. - Use the sight.
这样不好 先生
It's not right, sir.
赶紧找到老太太 否则你就被开除了
Find the old lady or you're dismissed.
快点
Now.
用心去看 丫头
Look inside, girl.
仔细看
Look deep.
她在哪
Where is she?
她迷路了 先生
She's lost, sir.
她如此孤单
She's so alone.
上帝啊 她头脑里有好多奇怪的东西
Oh, my Lord. So many strange things in her head.
但她在哪
But where?
她很兴奋
She was excited.
因为今晚的事
About tonight.
她去世之前 是想去见他
Before she passed on, she was going to see him.
他是谁 -那个伟大的人
Who's him? - The great man.
从伦敦一路而来 那个最最伟大的人
All the way from London, the great, great man.
狄更斯先生 狄更斯先生
Mr Dickens? Mr Dickens?
打扰了 狄更斯先生 该您上场了
Excuse me, sir, Mr Dickens, this is your call.
您还好吗 先生
Are you quite well, sir?
很好 我很好 抱歉
Splendid. Splendid. Sorry!
您该上场了 先生
Time you were on, sir.
当然了
Absolutely.
我只是一个人闷一会儿而已
I was just brooding...
今天是平安夜
Christmas Eve.
本就不该独自一个人
Not the best of times to be alone.
没人陪您来吗 先生
Did no-one travel with you, sir?
夫人没来前排观赏吗
No lady wife waiting out front?
怕是没有
I'm afraid not.
您若愿意 拙荆可以借您一用
You can have mine if you want.
我可不敢
Oh, I wouldn't dare.
一直以来 在关于家庭事务方面
I've, I've been rather... let's say, clumsy,
我可以说是笨拙的
with family matters.
谢天谢地 我已老得采不动花草了
Thank God I'm too old to cause any more trouble.
听您口气仿佛要退休了一般
You speak as if it's all over, sir.
怎么可能退休呢
Oh, it's never over!
一次又一次
On and on I go.
重复同样的表演
The same old show.
我就像个鬼魂
I'm like a ghost,
被诅咒永世重复经历这一切
condemned to repeat myself through all eternity.
现在也不晚的 先生
It's never too late, sir,
您还可以再想出一些新的故事
you could always think up some new turns.
我不行了
No, I can't.
就算是我 也有想象力枯竭的时候
Even MY imagination grows stale.
我老了
I'm an old man,
也许这辈子所有的想法都想完了
perhaps I've thought everything I will ever think.
不过万众瞩目的诱惑还是一如既往 对吧
Still. The lure of the limelight's as potent as a pipe, eh?
闪亮登场
On with the motley.
哎哟喂 -不准笑我
Blimey. - Don't laugh.
你看上去美极了
You look beautiful.
考虑到…
Considering.
考虑到什么
Considering what?
你是人类啊
That you're human.
我就当做是夸奖好了 你不换衣服吗
I think that's a compliment. Aren't you gonna change?
我换了衬衣 快来吧
I've changed my jumper! Come on.
你不许动 上次就是你先
You stay there, you've done this before.
这次该我了
This is mine.
准备好了吗
Ready for this?
来吧
Here we go.
走进历史
History.
她就在里面 先生 我确信
She's in there, sir, I'm certain of it.
很好
Right.
航线出了点问题
I got the flight a bit wrong.
无所谓 -不是1860年 是1869年
I don't care. - It's not 1860, it's 1869.
无所谓 -而且也不是那不勒斯
I don't care. - And it's not Naples.
我真不在乎 -是卡迪夫
I don't care. - It's Cardiff.
好吧
Right.
这会儿
Now, it is a fact
那个门环实实在在
that there was nothing particular at all
没有一点特殊的地方
about the knocker on the door of this house
现在请随便哪一位 要是可以的话
but let any man explain to me,
给我解释一下 那是怎么发生的
if he can, how it happened that Scrooge,
斯克鲁奇把他的钥匙插进门锁以后
having his key in the lock of the door,
看到那个门环
saw in the knocker,
没有经过任何中间的变化过程
without its undergoing any intermediate process of change,
却已不再是门环 而是马莱的脸
not a knocker, but Marley's face!
马莱的脸哪
Marley's face!
它看着斯克鲁奇
It looked at Scrooge
眼神像往常一样
as Marley used to look.
就像
It looked like...
我的天呐
Oh, my Lord...
就像 就像她一样
it looked... like that!
这是什么戏法
What phantasmagoria is this?
这还差不多
That's more like it.
请诸位坐回座位上
Stay in your seats, I, I beg you!
这只是彩灯戏法而已 是假的
It is a lantern show, trickery!
她在那儿 先生
There she is, sir!
我看见了
I can see that!
全世界都看见了
Whole bloomin' world can see that!
妙极了
Fantastic!
你看见那东西从哪来的了吗
Did you see where it came from?
看哪 幕后主使现身了 是不是
Ah! The wag reveals himself, does he?
这下你满意了吧 先生
I trust you're satisfied, sir!
你们 放开她
Oi! Leave her alone.
博士 我去追他们
Doctor! I'll get them.
小心
Be careful!
它说什么了吗 会说话吗
Did it say anything? Can it speak?
顺便说一下 我是博士
I'm the Doctor, by the way.
博士 你看起来像个苦工
Doctor? You look more like a navvy.
这衬衫有什么问题吗
What's wrong with this jumper?
你在干什么
What are you doing?
真不幸啊 小姐
A tragedy, miss.
不劳您忧心 交由我和主人应付即可
Don't worry yourself, me and the master'll deal with it.
其实这位可怜的夫人得了脑膜炎
Fact is, this poor lady's been taken with a brain-fever
我们必须要将她送去医院
and we have to get her to the infirmary.
她都凉了 她死了
She's cold. She's dead.
我的天呐 你们对她做了什么
Oh, my God, what did you do to her?
你这是做什么
What did you do that for?
她知道的太多了
She's seen too much!
把她抬进灵车里 去抬腿
Get her in the hearse! Legs!
煤气
Gas.
那东西是煤气构成的
It's made of gas.
洛斯 -你休想跑 先生
Rose! - You're not escaping me, sir!
你对那鬼怪了解多少
What do you know about that hob-goblin?
我估计是使用玻璃投影 谁指使你的
Projection on glass, I suppose. Who put you up to it?
伙计 现在没空 多谢
Yeah, mate, not now, thanks.
你 跟着那辆灵车
Oi! You! Follow that hearse!
先生 我做不到 -为什么
Can't do that, sir. - Why not?
为什么 我来告诉你为什么
Why not? I'll give you a very good reason why not.
因为这是我的马车
Because this is my coach.
那就快上车啊
Well, get in, then!
走
Move!
快点 你快跟丢了
Come on, you're losing them!
您没事吧 狄更斯先生
Everything in order, Mr. Dickens?
怎么会没事 -他叫你什么
No, it is not! - What did he say?
我先说 我并不是没有幽默感…
Let me say this first. I am not without a sense of humour...
狄更斯 -是我
Dickens? -Yes.
查尔斯·狄更斯
Charles Dickens?
对 -鼎鼎大名的查尔斯·狄更斯吗
-Yes! -THE Charles Dickens?
需要我赶走他吗 先生
Should I remove the gentleman, sir?
查尔斯·狄更斯 你真是才华横溢
Charles Dickens,You're brilliant, you are!
彻彻底底的天才啊 你的书我都读过
Completely, 100% brilliant! I've read 'em all!
《远大前程》《雾都孤儿》
Great Expectations, Oliver Twist,
那部讲鬼魂的叫什么来着
and what's the other one, the one with the ghost?
《圣诞颂歌》吗
Christmas Carol?
不不不 是和火车有关的
No, no, no, the one with the trains.
《信号员》没错就是它 特别恐怖
The Signalman, that's it, terrifying!
史上最棒的短篇小说
The best short story ever written!
你真是个天才
You're a genius.
需要我赶走他吗 先生
Do you want me to get rid of him, sir?
不必 让他待在这吧
Er, no, I think he can stay.
说真的 查尔斯
Honestly, Charles... er,
我能直呼你名吗 我是你的忠实粉丝啊
can I call you Charles? I'm such a big fan.
你说什么 忠实什么
Eh, you're a what? A big what?
粉丝 头号粉丝就是我
Fan. Number one fan, that's me!
你怎么会是"风扇"呢
How exactly are you a "fan"?
你哪里像那个给人带来凉爽的东西啊
In what way do you resemble a means of keeping oneself cool?
粉丝是指狂热者 崇拜你 痴迷于你
No, it means fanatic. Give over to you, mind you.
话说《马丁·索威特》里面那个美国人
For God's sake, that American bit in Martin Chuzzlewit,
是怎么回事
what's that about?
只是纯粹为了凑字数吗 太糟糕了
Was that just padding or what? It's rubbish.
你不是说是我的粉丝吗
I thought you were my fan?
好吧 要是你没法接受批评
Oh, well, if you can't take criticism...
继续写出像《老古玩店》那样的结局吧
Go on, do the death of Little Nell.
那真是太感人了
It cracks me up.
抱歉 不聊这些了
No! Sorry! Forget about that.
快点 再快点
Come on! Faster!
话说回来 到底谁在那辆灵车里
By the way, who exactly is in that hearse?
我朋友 她才19岁 都是我的错
My friend. She's only 19 and it's my fault.
我本该照顾好她 现在却让她遇到危险
She's in my care, now she's in danger.
那干嘛还要浪费时间谈那些老掉牙的小说
Why are we wasting my time talking about dry old books?
这件事重要得多呢 车夫
This is much more important. Driver!
动作快点 追上去 -遵命 先生
Be swift! The chase is on! - Yes, sir!
太好了 查理 -从来没人这么叫
Attaboy, Charlie. - Nobody calls me Charlie.
女人们都这么叫你 -你怎么知道
The ladies do. - How do you know that?
我早说过了 我可是头号…
I told you! I'm your number one...
头号粉丝
Number one fan.
这位可怜的女孩还活着呢 先生
The poor girl's still alive, sir,
您打算怎么处理她
what are we going to do with her?
我不知道
I don't know!
我本来没打算这么做的
I didn't plan any of this, did I?
死人莫名复活难道还是我的错吗
Is it my fault if the dead won't stay dead?
那是谁的错 先生
Then whose fault is it, sir?
为什么这种事总发生在我们身上
Why is this happening to us?
我以前帮过主教一个忙
I did the Bishop a favour once.
把他侄子化装成天使模样
Made his nephew look like a cherub
他侄子可是在河浜里死了两个礼拜
even though he'd been a fortnight in the weir.
说不定他能优惠点为我们驱邪
Hey, perhaps he'll do us an exorcism on the cheap!
说我不在 告诉他们店已打烊
Say I'm not in. Tell 'em we're closed.
就…让他们走开就行
Just, just, get rid of 'em.
先生们抱歉 本店已打烊
I'm sorry sir, we're closed.
乱说 什么时候殡仪馆也正常上下班了
Nonsense, since when did an undertaker keep office hours?
随时都会有人死亡 我要求见你们老板
The dead don't die on schedule, I demand to see your master.
他不在 先生
He's not in, sir.
别骗我 孩子 把老板叫来
Don't lie to me, child, summon the master!
非常抱歉 狄更斯先生
I'm awfully sorry, Mr Dickens,
但老板现在身体不适
but the master is indisposed.
你们家煤气出故障了吗
Having trouble with your gas?
到底在搞什么鬼
What the Shakespeare is going on?
你没事吧
Are you all right?
你在恶作剧吧 只是恶作剧吧
You're kidding me, yeah? You're just kidding.
只是在逗我玩吧
You are kidding me, aren't you?
好吧 不是恶作剧
OK, not kidding.
先生您不能进去
You're not allowed inside, sir.
墙里面有动静
There's something inside the walls.
煤气管道
The gas pipes.
某种东西住在煤气里
Something's living inside the gas.
放我出去 快开门
Let me out! Open the door!
是她 -救命啊 放我出去
That's her! - Please, let me out!
你们怎么就这么闯进来 这可是我家
How dare you, sir! This is my house.
我怎么跟你说的
I told you...
放我出去 谁来开下门啊
Let me out, somebody open the door!
开门啊
Open the door!
她是我的舞伴
I think this is my dance.
恶作剧吧 我们一定是被催眠了
It's a prank. Must be. We're under some mesmeric influence.
我们没被催眠 是尸体复活了
No, we are not, the dead are walking.
你好 -你好 你朋友叫什么
Hi. - Hi. Who's your friend?
查尔斯·狄更斯 -好的
Charles Dickens. - OK.
我是博士 你们是谁 想要干什么
My name's the Doctor. Who are you, then? What do you want?
失败 打开裂缝 我们要死了
Failing! Open the rift. We're dying.
被困于此形态
Trapped in this form.
无法继续维持 救救我们
Cannot sustain. Help us.
先是给我下迷药 然后还绑架我
First you drug me, then you kidnap me,
别以为我不知道你的手在乱摸
and don't think I didn't feel your hands having a quick wander,
你个老色鬼
you dirty old man.
不许这样跟我说话
I won't be spoken to like this.
还把我关进满是僵尸的房间里
Then you sent me in a room full of zombies!
这还不够
And if that ain't enough,
你居然跑了 留我一个人等死
you swan off and leave me to die!
说话呀
So come on! Talk!
这不是我的错 是这房子的错
It's not my fault, it's this house!
这房子很早就有传闻
It always had a reputation.
闹鬼
Haunted.
但我从不把它当回事
But I never had much bother,
直到大概三个月前 那些死人
until about three months back. And then the stiffs...
那些…
The, erm...
那些离世者开始变得不安宁
the dear departed started getting restless.
荒唐
Tommyrot!
你也看到了
You witnessed it!
根本控制不住啊 先生
Can't keep the beggars down, sir.
他们会走
They walk.
最奇怪的是 虽然他们复活了…
And it's the queerest thing, but they hang onto scraps...
按您要求加了两块糖 先生
Two sugars, sir, just how you like it.
一个曾经是教堂司事的老头
One old fella, used to be a sexton,
差点就走进了他自己的追悼会现场
almost walked into his own memorial service.
就像那位老太太
Just like the old lady,
按照她的生前计划去看先生您的演出
going to your performance, sir, just as she'd planned.
荒谬至极
Morbid fancy.
查尔斯 你当时也在场
Oh, Charles, you were there.
我看到的只是幻象
I saw nothing but an illusion.
如果你想否认 就别浪费我的时间
If you're going to deny it, don't waste my time,
闭嘴就好
just shut up.
那些气体怎么回事
What about the gas?
那是最近出现的 以前从没看到过
That's new, sir. I never seen anything like that.
说明它越来越强 裂缝越来越大
Means it's getting stronger. The rift's getting wider,
有东西在穿过裂缝
and something's sneaking through.
裂缝是什么 -时间和空间的脆弱点
What's the rift? - A weak point in time and space.
两个世界的连接处
A connection between this place and another.
大多数鬼故事都是这个造成的
That's the cause of ghost stories, most of the time.
所以这房子才买得这么便宜
That's how I got the house so cheap,
鬼故事代代相传
stories going back generations.
黑暗中的回声 空中的奇怪歌声
Echoes in the dark. Queer songs in the air.
阴影般的感受
And this feeling, like a shadow
掠过心头
passing over your soul.
我也不介意说实话 这对做生意挺有好处
Mind you, truth be told, it's been good for business,
人们对我们这种阴森森的行当的想法也是这样
just what people expect from a gloomy old trade like mine.
这不可能
Impossible!
在找绳子吗
Checking for strings?
或者金属丝
Wires... perhaps.
肯定有什么机械装置才整出这诡计
There must be some mechanism behind this fraud.
别这样 查尔斯
Oh, come on, Charles.
好吧 我不该叫你闭嘴 我道歉
All right, I shouldn't have told you to shut up. I'm sorry.
但你算是拥有全世界顶尖聪明的脑袋
But you've got one of the best minds in the world
而且你也看到那些气体怪物了
and you saw those gas creatures.
我无法接受
I cannot accept that.
当人类尸体在腐烂时会怎么样
And what does the human body do, when it decomposes?
会分解产生气体
It breaks down. Produces gas.
这很适合那些气体怪物
Perfect home for these gas-things,
他们就像借助交通工具般借助尸气溜进来
they can slip inside, use it as a vehicle.
就像你的车夫和马车 -别说了
Just like your driver and his coach.- Stop it!
难道我对这个世界的认识全部错了吗
Can it be that I have the world entirely wrong?
不是错 只是还有许多有待学习
Not wrong. There's just more to learn.
我一直批判那些幻想家
I've always railed against the fantasists!
我和所有人一样爱幻象并痴迷于此
Oh, I loved an illusion as much as the next man, reveled in them,
但幻象就只是幻象
but that's exactly what they were, illusions.
和真实世界是不一样的
The real world is something else.
我一生致力于消除不公正对待
I dedicated myself to that-- injustices,
这个伟大的社会目标
the great social causes.
我希望我的贡献是有用的
I hoped that I was a force for good.
可你现在告诉我真实世界
Now, you tell me that the real world
却是幽灵和南瓜灯的地盘
is a realm of spectres and Jack o'lanterns.
这样的话
In which case...
我是否虚度了这短暂人生 博士
have I wasted my brief span here, Doctor?
我的生命是否毫无价值
Has it all been for nothing?
小姐 你不该来帮忙的 这不合礼节
Please, miss, you shouldn't be helping, it's not right.
别说笑了
Don't be daft,
我打赌斯尼德让你干的活一定多得累死人
I bet Sneed works you to death.
你的工钱多少
How much do you get paid?
一年八英镑 小姐
Eight pound a year, miss.
多少
How much?
我知道 但我能有六英镑就知足了
I know! I would've been happy with six.
那你上过学吗
So did you even go to school, or what?
当然 你以为我是文盲吗
Of course I did, what do you think I am, an urchin?
我每周日都准时去上课
I went every Sunday, nice and proper.
什么 一周一次
What, once a week?!
学数学还有其他内容
We did sums and everything.
说实话
To be honest,
我特别讨厌上学 -我也是
I hated every second. - Me, too!
别告诉其他人
Don't tell anyone...
有一周我没去上课 一个人跑去荒地玩
but one week I didn't go and I ran down the Heath, all on my own.
这种事我干得多呢
I did plenty of that,
我以前经常和我同学席琳溜出去逛商店
I used to go round the shops with my mate, Shareen.
还经常跑去看男孩子
And we used to go and look at boys.
这个我就不清楚了 小姐
Well, I don't know much about that, miss.
拜托 时代不会相差这么多吧
Oh, come on, times haven't changed that much.
我打赌你也干过 -我没有 小姐
I bet you've done the same. - I don't think so, miss.
格温妮丝 你可以告诉我
Gwyneth, you can tell me.
我猜你肯定有心上人了
I bet you've got your eye on someone.
我想 确实有这么一个人
I suppose, there is one lad.
屠夫家的孩子 每周二过来
The butcher's boy, he comes by every Tuesday.
他的笑容特别可爱
Such a lovely smile on him.
我喜欢可爱的笑容
I like a nice smile.
可爱的微笑 迷人的翘臀
Good smile, nice bum.
我倒是第一次听说这种说法
Well, I have never heard the like!
约他出来 喝杯茶什么的 这是开始
Ask him out. Give him a cup of tea or something, that's a start.
我发誓这是我见过最奇怪的事了 小姐
I swear, it's the strangest thing, miss.
你穿着得体还如此有教养
You've got all the clothes and the breeding.
但是说的话却这么疯狂
But you talk like some sort of wild thing.
也许我就是如此
Maybe I am.
说不定这是好事
Maybe that's a good thing.
你的人生不能只局限在斯尼德先生这里
You need a bit more in your life than Mr Sneed.
不该这样说
Oh, no, that's not fair.
老斯尼德也没有那么坏
He's not so bad, old Sneed.
他很好心地收留了我
He was very kind to me to take me in,
我12岁时我的父母死于流感
cos I lost my mum and dad to the flu when I was 12.
抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
谢谢您 小姐 不过我们总会团聚的
Thank you, Miss. But I'll be with them again, one day.
和他们在天堂里重逢
sitting with them in Paradise.
如果我幸运的话
I shall be so blessed.
他们一定在天上等我
They're waiting for me.
说不定您父亲也在天上等着您呢 小姐
Maybe your dad's up there waiting for you too, Miss.
说不定吧
Maybe.
谁告诉你我爸爸已经过世了的
Um, who told you he was dead?
不知道 应该是博士说的
I dunno, must've been the Doctor.
我父亲几年前就死了
My father died years back.
但您最近都在想他 比以往更想
You've been thinking about him lately. More than ever.
应该吧
Suppose so.
你怎么知道的
How do you know all this?
斯尼德说我想得太多了
Mr. Sneed says I think too much,
我老是一个人在这里
I'm all alone down here.
我打赌您肯定有好多佣人 对不对小姐
I bet you've got dozens of servants, haven't you, miss?
不 我在的地方可没有佣人
No, no servants where I'm from.
您从那么远的地方过来
And you've come such a long way.
你为什么这么认为
What makes you think so?
你是从伦敦来的
You're from London.
我在画上看过伦敦的样子 但你的不一样
I've seen London in drawings, but never like that,
人们都行色匆匆
all those people rushing about.
还有半裸的 简直不知廉耻
Half-naked, for shame.
还有那些噪音
And the noise...
还有跑来跑去的金属盒子
and the metal boxes racing past...
还有飞在空中的鸟
and the birds in the sky!
不 鸟也是金属做的
No, no, they're metal as well.
金属鸟里都是人
Metal birds with people in them.
人在天上飞
People are flying.
而你 你飞得那么远
And you. You've flown so far.
比谁都远
Further than anyone.
你见到的东西
The things you've seen.
那些黑暗
The darkness.
大恶狼
The big Bad Wolf.
对不起 对不起 小姐 -没事
I'm sorry. I'm sorry, Miss. - It's all right.
我控制不住 我从小就这样
I can't help it. Ever since I was a little girl,
我妈妈说我有特殊的视力
my mum said I had the sight.
她叫我把这种能力隐藏起来
She told me to hide it.
但是现在这种能力越来越强大了 是吗
But it's getting stronger. More powerful. Is that right?
一直在增长 先生
All the time, sir.
每天晚上
Every night,
我都会听到脑海中有人说话
voices in my head.
你在那个裂口边上长大
You grew up on top of the rift.
你是它的一部分
You're part of it.
你就是钥匙
You're the key.
我也想弄清楚是怎么回事 先生
I've tried to make sense of it, sir.
咨询过
Consulted with...
各种各样的灵媒 巫师
spiritualists, table-rappers, all sorts.
这应该有点帮助
Well, that should help.
你能教我们该怎么办
You can show us what to do.
什么怎么办 先生
What to do where, sir?
我们准备来一场降神会
We're going to have a seance.
莫罗克太太在布特镇时
This is how Madame Mortlock summons
就是这么召唤出迷雾之都的幽灵的
those from the Land of Mists, down in Butetown.
来吧 我们得把手拉起来
Come. We must all join hands.
我不会参与这种事
I can't take part in this.
反悔了吗 来吧 思想放开点
Humbug? Come on. Open mind.
我就是专门揭穿这种廉价把戏的
This is precisely the sort of cheap mummery I strive to unmask.
降神会
Seances!
不就是用几面闪闪的鼓
Nothing but luminous tambourines
和藏在膝盖间的小风琴故弄玄虚吗
and a squeeze-box concealed between the knees.
这姑娘什么都不知道
This girl knows nothing!
现在先别急着反对
Now, don't antagonise her.
我更喜欢看到一个快乐的灵媒
I love a happy medium.
真不敢相信你能说出这种话
I can't believe you just said that.
来吧 我们说不定需要你
Come on. We might need you.
好样的
Good man.
格温妮丝 来吧
Now, Gwyneth.
召唤吧
Reach out.
和我们说话吧
Speak to us.
你在么
Are you there?
降临吧 幽灵
Spirits, come.
向我们倾诉 让我们减轻你的负担
Speak to us that we may relieve your burden.
你听到了没
Can you hear that?
什么都不会发生的 这太愚蠢了
Nothing can happen, this is sheer folly.
快看她
Look at her.
我看到它们了
I see them!
我感觉到它们了
I feel them!
它在说什么 -它没法通过裂口
What's it saying? - It can't get through the rift.
格温妮丝 不是它在控制你
Gwyneth, it's not controlling you,
而是你在控制它
you're controlling it.
现在注视着它们 让它们通过
Now look deep. Allow them through.
我不行
I can't.
你可以的 相信自己
Yes, you can. Just believe it.
我对你有信心 格温妮丝
I have faith in you, Gwyneth.
和它们联结起来
Make the link.
好了
Yes!
上帝啊
Great God!
另一个世界的幽灵
Spirits from the other side!
应该是宇宙的另一端
The other side of the universe.
可怜可怜我们吧
Pity us!
可怜可怜格尔斯吧
Pity the Gelth!
时间所剩不多 帮帮我们
There is so little time. Help us!
你要我们怎么做
What do you want us to do?
裂口 把这个女孩带到裂口那去
The rift. Take the girl to the rift.
建立连接
Make the bridge.
为什么
What for?
我们已经所剩不多了
We are so very few.
我们最后的族人
The last of our kind.
我们面临着灭亡
We face extinction!
为什么 发生什么了
Why, what happened?
我们也曾有过肉体 和你们一样
Once we had a physical form, like you.
但是战争来临了
But then the War came.
什么战争 -时间大战
War? What war? - The Time War.
整个宇宙发生了剧变
The whole universe convulsed.
时间大战对于低等种族来说毫无影响
The Time War raged, invisible to smaller species
但是对于高级种族来说却是毁灭性的
but devastating to higher forms.
我们的躯体都毁灭了
Our bodies wasted away.
我们只能以气体的形式存在
We're trapped in this gaseous state.
所以你们才需要这些尸体
So that's why you need the corpses.
我们想挺直身板
We want to stand tall.
感受阳光的温度
To feel the sunlight.
再次感受生命
To live again.
我们需要肉体 而你们却在丢弃尸体
We need a physical form and your dead are abandoned.
它们都被浪费了 给我们吧
They go to waste. Give them to us.
可是不行
But we can't.
为什么不行
Why not?
这不… 我是说这不
It's not... I mean,it's not...
不体面还是不礼貌 这样能救它们的命
Not decent? Not polite? It could save their lives.
打开裂口吧
Open the rift.
让格尔斯过来吧
Let the Gelth through.
我们正在消逝 救救我们
We're dying. Help us.
可怜可怜格尔斯吧
Pity the Gelth!
格温妮丝
Gwyneth!
都是真的
All true.
全都是真的
It's all true.
没关系 你躺着就行
It's all right. You just sleep.
但我的天使呢 小姐
But my angels, Miss!
它们来了 是吗 它们需要我
They came, didn't they? They need me.
它们的确需要你 格温妮丝
They do need you, Gwyneth.
你是它们存活的唯一机会
You're their only chance of survival.
跟你说过了 别来烦她
I told you, leave her alone.
她累坏了 你的战争也不该她来打
She's exhausted and she's not fighting your battles.
来把这个喝了
Now, drink this.
你说什么 博士 再解释一遍
But what did you say, Doctor? Explain it again.
它们是什么 -外星人
What are they? - Aliens.
你是说 就像外国人一样吗
Like, foreigners, you mean?
非常远的外国 从上面来的
Pretty foreign, yeah. From up there.
布雷肯吗 -差不多
Brecon? - Close.
它们想从布雷肯去卡迪夫
And they've been trying to get through from Brecon to Cardiff
但是路堵住了
but the road's blocked.
只有一部分人可以通过
Only a few can get through.
不仅如此 它们还很虚弱
Even then, they're weak.
它们只能控制那些躯体一小段时间
They can only test-drive the bodies for so long.
然后就得转回气体形态 躲回管道里
Then they have to revert to gas and hide in the pipes.
所以它们才需要那个女孩吗
Which is why they need the girl?
不能把她给它们 -但她能帮忙
They're not having her. - But she can help.
她成为了那个裂口的一部分
Living on the rift she's become part of it.
她能打开裂口 建立连接让他们通过
She can open it up, make a bridge and let them through.
难以置信 幽灵其实不是鬼魂
Incredible. Ghosts that are not ghosts
而是从另一个世界来的生灵
but beings from another world.
只能靠寄生在尸体上才能活在我们的世界里
Who can only exist in our realm by inhabiting cadavers.
这套办法挺不错 说不定能行
Good system. It might work.
你不能让它们寄生在死人身体里乱跑
You can't let them run around inside of dead people!
为什么不行 就跟循环利用一样
Why not? It's like recycling.
说真的 不行 -说真的 可以
Seriously though, you can't. - Seriously though, I can.
可这样做就是不对
But it's just wrong.
那些尸体都曾是活生生的人
Those bodies were living people.
就算死了我们也应该尊重他们
We should respect them, even in death.
你带着捐献同意书吗
Do you carry a donor card?
这不一样 这 -本来就不一样
It's different, that's... - It is different, yeah.
我这里道德标准不一样 要么适应 要么回家
It's a different morality. Get used to it. Or go home.
你也听到了 它们说时间不多了
You heard what they said, time's short.
最后几个格尔斯快死了
I can't worry about a few corpses
我没空来管几具尸体的事
when the last of the Gelth could be dying.
我不管 它们不能利用她
I don't care, they're not using her.
我能说句话吗 小姐
Don't I get a say, Miss?
可以 哦不
Well, yes... no.
你不明白发生了什么
You don't understand what's going on.
小姐 你会这么说
You would say that, Miss,
是因为你已经在脑子里下了定论
cos that's very clear inside your head.
你以为我很笨
That you think I'm stupid.
不是这样的 -但事实如此
That's not fair. - It's true though.
可能你来的地方 事情完全不一样
Things might be very different where you're from,
但此时此刻 我知道我在想什么
but here and now, I know my own mind.
我的天使们需要我
And the angels need me.
博士 我应该干什么
Doctor? What do I have to do?
你什么都不用干
You don't have to do anything.
小时候它们就一直对着我唱歌
They've been singing to me since I was a child.
我觉得它们是我妈妈派来照顾我的
Sent by my mum on holy mission,
告诉我该怎么办
so tell me.
我们得找到裂口
We need to find the rift.
这房子就建在一个薄弱点上
This house is on a weak-spot,
所以肯定有个地方的束缚是最弱的
so there must be a spot that's weaker than any other.
斯尼德先生 这房子最弱的地方在哪里
Mr Sneed, what's the weakest part of this house?
幽灵最多的地方在哪里
The place where most of the ghosts have been seen?
那肯定是停尸房了
That would be the morgue.
估计你也不会说露台之类的地方
No chance you were going to say gazebo, is there?
这才是真正的"荒凉山庄"
Talk about bleak house.
事实是 博士
The thing is, Doctor,
格尔斯不会成功 因为我知道他们没有成功
the Gelth don't succeed, cos I know they don't.
我知道1869年尸体没有满大街跑
I know for a fact that corpses weren't walking round in 1869.
时间是不断变化的 每一秒都在改变
Time's in flux, changing every second.
你那舒适的小天地很有可能就此改写
Your cosy little world could be rewritten like that.
没有绝对安全的事 记住 根本没有
Nothing is safe. Remember that. Nothing.
博士 我觉得这房间越来越冷了
Doctor, I think the room is getting colder.
他们来了
Here they come.
你们来帮我们了
You've come to help!
赞美博士 赞美他
Praise the Doctor! Praise him.
你们要保证不会伤害她
Promise you won't hurt her.
快点 求你了 时间不多了
Hurry! Please! So little time.
可怜可怜格尔斯吧
Pity the Gelth!
你们过来之后我会带你们去别的地方
I'll take you somewhere else after the transfer.
去一个你们能拥有正常身体的地方
Somewhere you can build proper bodies.
这只是暂时的解决办法 明白吗
This isn't a permanent solution, all right?
我的天使们 我能帮他们活下去
My angels! I can help them live.
薄弱点在哪里 -这里 拱门下方
OK, where's the weak point? - Here, beneath the arch!
拱门下方
Beneath the arch.
你没必要这么做
You don't have to do this.
我的天使们
My angels.
建立连接
Establish the bridge!
连接虚空 让我们通过吧
Reach out to the void. Let us through!
好的
Yes!
我能看见你们
I can see you.
我能看见你们 来吧
I can see you! Come!
连接正在建立
Bridgehead establishing.
到我这里来 到这个世界来
Come to me. Come to this world.
可怜的迷路的灵魂
Poor lost souls.
开始了 连接建立完毕
It has begun! The bridge is made.
她献身给了格尔斯
She has given herself to the Gelth!
数量挺多啊
Rather a lot of them, eh?
连接通畅 我们来了
The bridge is open. We descend.
格尔斯将强行通过
The Gelth will come through in force.
你说过你们为数不多
You said that you were few in number!
几十亿而已 我们都需要尸体
A few billion! And all of us in need of corpses!
格温妮丝
Now, Gwyneth,
停下来
stop this.
听主人的话
Listen to your master!
这已经过分了 别闹了 孩子
This has gone far enough, stop dabbling,child,
别管他们了 我求你了
and leave these things alone, I beg of you.
斯尼德先生 快回来 -别靠近
Mr Sneed, get back! - Don't go near.
我开始觉得有点不对劲了
I think it's going a little bit wrong.
我加入了格尔斯军团
I have joined the legions of the Gelth.
来吧 和我们一起进军 -天呐
Come, march with us. - Oh, glory!
我们需要躯体 你们所有人 必死
We need bodies. All of you, dead.
全人类 必死
The human race, dead.
格温妮丝 阻止他们 送他们回去 快
Gwyneth, stop them! Send them back, now!
又有三具躯体 占有它们
Three more bodies! Convert them!
把它们变成承载格尔斯之肉身
Make them vessels for the Gelth!
博士 我无法陪伴你们了 抱歉
Doctor, I can't! I'm sorry.
你们带来的新世界 我无法接受
This new world of yours, it's too much for me.
我实在
I'm so...
献身荣耀吧
Give yourself to glory.
将你们的生命献给格尔斯
Sacrifice your lives to the Gelth.
我还相信了你们 同情了你们
I trusted you. I pitied you!
我们不需要你的同情
We don't want your pity!
我们需要这个世界和其中所有躯体
We want this world and all its flesh.
只要我还活着你们就休想
Not while I'm alive.
那就去死吧
Then live no more.
但是我不能死 告诉我我不会死
But I can't die. Tell me I can't.
这个年代我都还没出生 我怎么可能死呢
I haven't even been born yet, it's impossible for me to die.
对不对
Isn't it?
抱歉
I'm sorry.
好难受 这种气体对我们有害
Failing! Atmosphere hostile!
煤气
Gas!
原来是煤气
The gas!
这是1869年 我怎么能死在这一年
But it's 1869, how can I die now?
时间不是直线 可能被扭曲成任何形状
Time isn't a straight line, it can twist into any shape.
你可以在二十世纪出生 在十九世纪死去
You can be born in the 20th century and die in the 19th.
都是我的错
And it's all my fault.
是我带你来这里的
I brought you here.
不是你的错
It's not your fault.
是我自己要来的
I wanted to come.
那我呢 我见过特洛伊城的衰败
What about me? I saw the fall of Troy,
见过第五次世界大战
World War Five.
还推动了波士顿茶会
I pushed boxes at the Boston Tea Party.
现在我却要死在地牢里
Now I'm gonna die in a dungeon,
还是在卡迪夫
in Cardiff!
不止是死
And it's not just dying.
我们会成为他们中的一员
We're gonna become one of them.
我们死也要战死 -好
We'll go down fighting, yeah? - Yeah.
一起战死 -好
Together? - Yeah.
我非常高兴遇见了你
I'm so glad I met you.
我也是
Me, too.
博士 博士
Doctor! Doctor!
把火灭了 开大煤气
Turn off the flame, turn up the gas.
把房间充满煤气 赶快
Now fill the room! All of it, now.
你在干什么 -把它们都开大
What are you doing? - Turn it all on!
把房间充满煤气
Flood the place!
聪明 煤气
Brilliant, gas!
怎么 我们打算改为被煤气呛死吗
What, so we choke to death instead?
我想得对吗 博士
Am I correct, Doctor?
这些生物是气态的
These creatures are gaseous.
把房间充满煤气 能把它们拉离宿主
Fill the room with gas. It'll draw them out of the host,
被吸到外面 就像毒液被吸出伤口
suck them into the air, like poison from a wound.
我希望
I hope...
天呐
Oh, lord!
我希望这个理论能被证实 最好快点
I hope that this theory will be validated... soon.
当然立即见效最好
If not immediately.
煤气多得是
Plenty more.
有效果了
It's working!
格温妮丝 送他们回去
Gwyneth, send them back.
他们说谎了 他们不是天使
They lied, they're not angels!
骗子
Liars?
看看他们
Look at them!
如果你的父母在天有灵 看到这场面
If your mother and father could look down and see this,
他们也会这样说
they'd tell you the same.
他们会给你力量 快送他们回去
They'd give you the strength. Now send them back!
我无法呼吸了 -查尔斯 带她出去
Can't breathe. - Charles, get her out.
我不会离开她 -他们太强大了
I'm not leaving her. - They're too strong.
还记得你看过的那个世界吗
Remember that world you saw?
洛斯的世界 那些人们
Rose's world? All those people.
除非你把他们送回裂口
None of it will exist
不然他们都不会存在
unless you send them back through the rift!
我无法送他们回去
I can't send them back.
但我能困住他们
But I can hold them.
把他们约束在这里 这个房间里
Hold them in this place. Hold them here.
出去
Get out.
你不能这么做
You can't!
离开这个房间
Leave this place.
洛斯 出去 快点
Rose, get out, go now.
我肯定会救她脱险的 快走
I won't leave her while she's still in danger. Now go!
来吧 把它给我
Come on. Leave that to me.
这边走
This way!
抱歉
I'm sorry.
多谢
Thank you.
她没能逃出来
She didn't make it.
抱歉 她关闭了裂口
I'm sorry. She closed the rift.
付出了太大的代价
At such a cost.
可怜的孩子
The poor child.
我努力过 洛斯 但格温妮丝早已死去
I did try, Rose, but Gwyneth was already dead.
她至少五分钟前就死去了 -什么意思
She had been for at least five minutes. - What do you mean?
我认为她站在拱门下方那一刻就已经死了
I think she was dead from the minute she stood in that arch.
不可能
But she can't have,
她对我们说话 帮助我们 还救了我们
she spoke to us, she helped us, she saved us.
她怎么能做到的
How could she have done that?
天堂和人世间的事物
There are more things in Heaven and Earth
要比你能想象的多得多
than are dreamt of in your philosophy.
即便对你也是 博士
Even for you, Doctor.
她拯救了这个世界
She saved the world.
一个女佣
A servant girl.
却没人会知道
And no-one will ever know.
好了 小查理 我这就要回我的
Right then, Charlie boy, I've just got to go into my, erm...
小木屋了
shed.
不用很久
Won't be long.
你接下来要怎么办
What are you going to do now?
我要坐邮车返回伦敦
I shall take the mail-coach back to London,
尽快回去
quite literally post-haste.
我不能再这般独自一人了
This is no time for me to be on my own.
我要与家人共度圣诞 弥补过失
I shall spend Christmas with my family and make amends to them.
见识过今晚的一切后
After all I've learnt tonight,
我明白了家人才是最重要的
there can be nothing more vital.
你振作起来了 -非常振作
You've cheered up. - Exceedingly!
早晨我还以为我通晓世间万物
This morning, I thought I knew everything in the world.
但现在才知道那只是冰山一角
Now I know I've just started.
那些宏大又绝妙的见解 博士
All these huge and wonderful notions, Doctor!
我受到了启发 我一定要写写它们的故事
I am inspired, I must write about them!
你认为这样好吗
Do you think that's wise?
我会谨慎处理的 开始的时候
I shall be subtle, at first.
《艾德温·德鲁德之谜》还缺个结局
The Mystery Of Edwin Drood still lacks an ending.
也许凶手不是男孩的叔叔
Perhaps the killer was not the boy's uncle.
也许凶手根本不属于这个世界
Perhaps he was not of this earth!
《艾德温·德鲁德之谜》和《蓝色元素》
The Mystery Of Edwin Drood And The Blue Elementals!
我要广为传播 揭示真相
I can spread the word, tell the truth!
那祝你好运了
Good luck with it.
很高兴见到你 太棒了
Nice to meet you, fantastic.
那么再见 多谢
Bye, then. And thanks.
亲爱的
Oh, my dear!
真新潮
How modern.
谢谢 但我不明白
Thank you. But I don't understand,
这是什么告别呢
in what way is this goodbye?
你们要去哪里
Where are you going?
你马上就知道了 我进去了
You'll see. In the shed.
发自内心地说 博士
Upon my soul, Doctor,
和你一起真是谜题不断
it's one riddle after another with you.
但在揭露这些真相后
But after all these revelations,
还有一个谜你没有解释
there's one mystery you still haven't explained.
告诉我
Answer me this.
你是谁
Who are you?
只是一个路过的朋友
Just a friend. Passing through.
但你对未来世界了解甚多
But you have such knowledge of future times.
我不希望勉强你 但我想问你
I don't wish to impose on you but I must ask you,
我写的书 博士
my books... Doctor.
它们流传了吗 -当然
Do they last? - Oh, yes.
流传了多久
For how long?
永远
Forever.
好了
Right.
小屋 进去吧 洛斯
Shed. Come on, Rose.
什么 进这个盒子
What? In the box?
你们俩都进去
Both of you?
冷静 伙计
Down, boy.
再会
See ya.
如果他写蓝色的鬼魂 不就改变历史了吗
Doesn't that change history, if he writes about blue ghosts?
一个星期后就是1870年
In a week's time, it's 1870.
他的大限将至 很遗憾
And that's the year he dies. Sorry.
他无法将这个故事讲给世人听了
He'll never get to tell his story.
不 他这么好
Oh, no. He was so nice.
但是在你的时代 他已经死了
But in your time, he was already dead.
我们已经使他复活了
We've brought him back to life
比任何时候都生龙活虎 老查理
and he's more alive now than he's ever been. Old Charlie Boy.
让我们给他最后一个惊喜
Let's give him one last surprise.
圣诞快乐 先生 -你也圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas, sir. - Merry Christmas to you!
上帝保佑我们
God bless us.
保佑所有人
Every one.
下集预告
飞碟坠落伦敦 大本钟被毁
一架飞碟坠落于伦敦中央导致大本钟被毁
Big Ben destroyed as a UFO crash lands in Central London.
外星人应急响应及求助热线
你们已被逮捕 离开那个盒子
You are now under arrest. Step away from that box.
把手举过头顶 你们被捕了
Raise your hands above your head.
然后呢 它们是要入侵吗
What is it then? Are they invading?
多有趣的入侵方法 把全世界的人都惊到了
Funny way to invade, putting the world on red alert.
如果必要 我甚至可以对全国实施军事管制
My God, I'll put this country under marshal law if I have to.
启用Δ防御计划 快 出动 出动
Defence part Delta! Come on, move, move!
安全
Clear!